Guide to the Walter Freeman and James Watts collection, 1918-1988 MS0803.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Walter Freeman Papers, 1918-1972; MS0803 Series 1; 11.5 Linear feet (Box 19, Box 18, Box 17, Box 16, Box 15, Box 14, Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 12, Box 11, Box 50, Box 13, Box 21, Box 22)
  - Publications, 1918-1972; MS0803 Series 1.4
    - Symptomatic Epilepsy in One od the Identical Twins A study of the Epileptic Character, 1934 ca. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in Agitated Depression, 11/1936 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Diseases of the Cranial Nerves, 1937 ca. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Subcortical Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Certain Psychoses, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - An Interpretation of the Functions of the Frontal Lobe, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Intellectual and Emotional Changes Following Prefrontal Lobotomy, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - The Frontal Lobes and Consciousness of the Self, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - The Radical Treatment of the Psychoses and Neuroses, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence regarding reprints of "Prefrontal Lobotomy: The Surgical Relief of Mental Pain", 1943 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Convalescent Care and AIDS Rehabilitation, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Physiological Psychology, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Section of Psychology, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: The Problem of Schizophrenia, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Psychosurgery-The Problem of Deterioration, 1945 ca. (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Surgical Treatment of Mental Disorders, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Pain of Organic Disease Relieved by Prefrontal Lobotomy, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Survey of 331 cases, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Psychosurgery, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Psychosurgery Review, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Book review of "Doctor Freud: An Analysis and a Warning,", 1947 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Indications and Contraindications, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Psychosurgery, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Psychosurgery: The Nursing Problem, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Psychosurgery During 1936-1946, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Psychosurgery: Summary for GWU Publication, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Retrograde Degeneration of the Thalamus following Prefrontal Lobotomy, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - The Thalamic Projection to the Frontal Lobe, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Confidential from Washington: Psychosurgery, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - The Frontal Lobe Functions as Revealed by Psychosurgery, 02/1948 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Pain mechanisms and the Frontal Lobes: A Study of Prefrontal Lobotomy for Intractable Pain, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Psychosurgery, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Psychosurgery for Pain, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Transorbital Leucotomy, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Transorbital Lobotomy: Preliminary Report of Ten Cases, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - Psychosurgery: Neuropsychiatric Aspects, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Psychosurgery: Neuropsychiatric Aspects, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Lesions of Transorbital Lobotomy, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Go South M.S: New Hope for Multiple Sclerosis, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - La Personalidad y Los Lobulos Frontales, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Psychosurgery, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Book review of "Frontal Lobes and Schizophrenia,", 1953 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Hazards of Lobotomy-Study of Two Thousand Operations, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Surgical Treatment of Mental Pain, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - The Contributions of Egas Moniz: An Appreciation From America, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Psychosurgery, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Partial list of Freeman publications, 1956-1973 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Egas Moniz (1874-1955): His Life and Work, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Section of psychiatry: Twenty Years of Leucotomy, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Psychosurgery, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Transorbital Lobotomy versus Electroconvulsive Therapy in the Treatment of Mentally Ill Tuberculous Patients, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Frontal Lobotomy: A Follow Up Study of 3000 Patients From One to Twenty Years, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Head And Shoulder Hunting in the Americas: Photographic Follow-up Studies in Lobotomy, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Final Report of 500 Freeman and Watts Patients Followed for 10 to 20 years, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Psychosurgery: Present Indications and Future Prospects, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - American Handbook of Psychiatry, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - The Founding of the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, Inc., 1959 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Northwest Medicine, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Psychiatric Developments in Santa Clara County, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Adolescents in Distress, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Adolescents in Distress Therapeutic Possibilities of Lobotomy, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Psychosurgery: A Quarter of A Century Later, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Lobotomy after 65, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Psychosurgery, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - West Virginia Lobotomy Project: A Sequel, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Psychosurgery, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Abstract and Comments on paper "Psychiatrists Who Kill Themselves", 1966 (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Multiple Lobotomies, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Psychiatrists Who Kill Themselves: A Study in Suicide, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Thorium Granulomas in the Brain: Report of 4 Cases Following Prefrontal Lobotomy, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Frontal Lobotomy in Early Schizophrenia Long Follow-up in 415 Cases, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - GW Medicine Magazine, including article on portrait dedications of Freeman and Watts, Spring, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Conference Papers and Lectures, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.5
    - Acidosis of Anasthesia, Undergraduate Medical Association of the University of Pennsylvania, 05/01/1919 (Box 15, Folder 41)
    - AMA convention, news clippings of exhibit by Freeman on facial movements of patients, 06/1931 (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - AMA Suggestions for Authors of Section Papers, undated (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - Brain Stem and Cerebellum of a Five Months' Fetus, Philadelphia Neurologic Society, 04/27/1923 (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - Breathless Women, Sequoia Hospital, Los Altos, CA., 08/12/1955 (Box 15, Folder 45)
    - Bulletin of the American College of Surgeons, 11/1953 ca. (Box 15, Folder 46)
    - Case of Endotheliomoa of Brain one year after operation, Neurologic Society of Philadelphia, 01/26/1923 (Box 15, Folder 47)
    - Cerebellar Atrophy, Philadelphia Neurological Society, 02/27/1931 (Box 15, Folder 48)
    - Crush of the Spinal Cord, American Society of Neurosurgeons, 06/14/1930 (Box 15, Folder 49)
    - The Crystallization of Insoluble Silver Salts by Precipitation in Gels, Undergraduate Medical Association of the University of Pennsylvania, 04/19/1917 (Box 15, Folder 50)
    - Depression: Current Concepts and Treatment, Palo Alto Stanford Hospital, 09/16/1959 (Box 15, Folder 51)
    - Effect of Acid and Alkali on Respiration, Undergraduate Medical Association of University of Pennsylvania, 05/01/1919 (Box 15, Folder 52)
    - Effect of Thorotrast Injections upon Ventricles and Subarachnoid Spaces, American Association of Neuropathologists, 1937 ca. (Box 15, Folder 53)
    - The Frontal Lobes and Conciousness of the Self, Hartford, CT, 01/1941 (Box 15, Folder 54)
    - Gastric Lues case presented before Pepper Medical Society, Mayo Clinic, 12/12/1919 (Box 15, Folder 56)
    - Glioma of Medulla, Philadelphia Neurological Society, 01/26/1923 (Box 15, Folder 57)
    - Hydronephrosis 4000 cc, Pathological Society of Philadelphia, 04/14/1921 (Box 15, Folder 58)
    - Interpretation of Frontal Lobe Function based upon observations in 46 cases of Prefrontal Lobotomy, Harvey Cushing Society, Yale University, 04/07/1939 (Box 15, Folder 59)
    - Lobotomy for Intractable Psychosomatic Disorders, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 60)
    - Lobotomy in Older People by Walter Freeman Aqnews State Hospital, 06/19/1959 (Box 15, Folder 61)
    - Conferences, Lectures papers: Multiple Cancer, Washington Society of Pathologists, 02/01/1930 (Box 15, Folder 62)
    - Conferences, Lectures papers: Multiple Cranial Nerve Palsies, Philadelphia Neurological Society, 01/27/1933 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Neurologic Emergencies, American Association of General Practitioners, San Mateo, CA, 11/26/1957 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Notes on Prefrontal Lobotomy: Paper presented at George Washington Faculty Luncheon, 10/21/1936 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Physical Treatments in Mental Disorders: Comparisons of Chemical, Electrical and Surgical Methods, VA Hospital, Roseburg, OR, 09/22/1959 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Final Report of 500 Freeman and Watts patients followed for 10 to 20 years, Southern Medical Association, Miami, FL, 11/11/1957-11/14/1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Conference, Papers, Lectures: Prefrontal Lobotomy in Agitated Depression: Report of a case, Medical Society of the District of Columbia, 10/01/1936 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Mental Disorders, Southern Medical Association, 11/20/1936 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Primary Myopathy, Washington Society of Pathologists, 02/01/1930 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Program, 24th Annual Scientific Assembly of the Medical Society of the District of Columbia, Washington, DC, 10/05/1953-10/07/1953 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Program, American College of Surgeons, Charlotte, NC, 02/01/1954-02/3/1954 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Program, American College of Surgeons Sectional Meeting, London, 05/17/1954-05/19/1954 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Program, American Psychiatric Association, Washington, DC, 05/17/1948-05/20/1948 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Program, Arizona Division of American Cancer Society, 01/14/1954-01/16/1954 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Program, Association of Military Surgeons, Washington, DC, 11/09/1953-11/11/1953 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Program, Program, International Conference on Psychosurgery, Lisbon, Portugal, 08/03/1948-08/07/1948 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Program, International League Against Epilepsy, Washington DC, 05/01/1954-05/02/1954 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Program, Proceedings of the Second Research Conference on Psychosurgery, New York, 06/02/1050--06/03/1950 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Program, Southern Medical Association, Atlanta, GA, 10/26/1953--10/29/1953 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Prophylaxis in the War as Evincing the Trend of Modern Medicine, Pepper Medical Society, University of Pennsylvania, 03/02/1917 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Psychiatrists Who Kill Themselves: A Study in Suicide, American Psychiatric Association, Detroit, MI, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Psychosurgery: An Evaluation of 200 cases Over Seven Years, Baltimore, 10/22/1943 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Psychosurgery: Results in 200 cases (Abstract), American Psychiatric Association, Philadelphia, PA, 05/1944 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - The Radical Treatment of the Psychoses: Alterations in the Personality Following Prefrontal Lobotomy, Montreal Neurological Institute, 12/1940 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Recent Advances in Psychosurgery, Washington Academy of Neurosurgery, 10/28/1964 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Results of Frontal Lobotomy, Association of General Hospital Psychiatrists, Boston, MA, 09/25/1968 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Schnizophrenia in Childhood: Its Modification by Prefrontal Lobotomy, Institute of Living, 02/26/1947 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Section on Nervous and Mental Diseases (transcript with Freeman's comments), 06/05/1941 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Strangulation of Penis by Finger Ring, Urologic Society, 11/28/1921 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Surgery Versus Drugs in the Treatment of Neuroses, Fresno County Medical Society, Fresno, CA, 02/12/1957 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Thorotrast in Neurologic Diagnosis, Baltimore Neurological Society, 01/1941 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Thorotrast Ventriculography, A.N.A., 1934 ca. (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Transorbital Lobotomy, Los Angeles, CA, 05/20/1955 (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Conference papers, Lectures: Visualization of the Spinal Cord and Roots of Lumbo Sacreal Plexus with Therotrast, Medical Society of the District of Columbia, 04/13/1939 (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - When to Use What in Psychiatry/Drugs Useful in Neurology, Neuropsychiatric Orientation for General Practice, 10/26/1058-10/28/1958 (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Research, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.6
    - Acute Hemrragic Inflammation of the Suprarenals: Report of Four Cases, St. Elizabeth's Hospital, 1930 ca. (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - Biometrical Studies in Psychiatry, 11/1928 (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - Brief case histories of 20 patients, undated (Box 16, Folder 37)
    - Cases of Xeroderma Pigmentosum Occuring in Brother and Sister, 1922 (Box 16, Folder 38)
    - The Cerebral Leucotome, n.a., undated (Box 16, Folder 39)
    - Critique of Somatic Therapies by Lauren Smith, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Drawings prepared by Walter Freeman (spinal segment, cerebellar system, sensory system, visual pathways, 1924 ca. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Five Year Follow-Up at Athens State Hospital, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - A Follow-up Study of Patients Treated by Thalamotomy and by Combined Frontal and Thalamic Lesions by E.A. Spiegel, et al, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Frontal Lobotomy 1936 -1956: A Follow-up Study of 3000 Patients from One to Twenty Years by Walter Freeman, 1956 ca. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - The Functions of the Frontal Lobes Based Upon Observations in 40 Cases of Prefrontal Lobotomy, 1939 ca. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Human Brain: Nature's Masterpiece of Engineering, 1925 ca. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Lobotomy: A Comparison of Prefrontal Lobotomy (Freeman and Watts) with Transorbital Lobotomy by Walter Freeman, 1950 ca. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 1950-1960 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Multiple Frontal Leucotomies and Other Psychosurgical Procedures: A Five to Ten Year Follow-up of 358 Cases, 1961 ca. (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Multiple Lobotomies: Inferences Drawn from 356 Cases, 11/1960 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Myoclonus Epilepsy, 1930 ca. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Observations on Medical Temporal Lobotomy and Uncotomy in the Treatment of Psychotic States y W.B. Scoville, et al. (abstract)., undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Paget's Disease of the Skull with Cerebral Compression, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Paralytic Torticollis (with photographs), 1930 ca. (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Pattern, Distribution and Properties of Electro-Encephalographic Rhythms from the Depth of the Frontal Lobe in 60 Psychotic Patients by Carl W. Sem-Jacobson, et al, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Persistent Attention and Psychosurgery by Mary Francis Robinson and Walter Freeman, 1955 ca. (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - A Pharmacological Study of Sodium Citrate, 1921 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy for Relief of Pain with a Report of a New Operative Technique by [Everett G.] Grantham, 1951 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Present Status of Lobotomy by William Beecher Scoville, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Psychosurgery: One Quarter Century Later by Walter Freeman, Discussion given by Douglass Goldman, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Results of Transorbital Lobotomy in 400 State Hospital Patients by William W. Wilson, et al., 1953 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Research: The Rhinencephalon in Man by W.B. Scoville, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Selective Lobotomy in the Treatment of Intractable Pain by Everett Grantham and R. Glen Spurling, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Senile Hemichorea with Contralateral Thalamic Syndrome, 1920 ca. (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Simple Method for Blood Group Determination, 1920 (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - Somatic, Intellectual & Emotional Change Following Prefrontal Lobotomy (abstract), 1935 ca. (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Some Subjective Experiences in Temporal Seizures, 1959 ca. (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Stereotaxic Thalamofrontal Radiotomy (abstract) by Tracy Putman and Stanford Rothenberg, undated (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Summary of Results of Prefrontal Lobotomy and Presentation of a Patient Operated upon for an Obsessive Compulsive State (abstract), 1943 ca. (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - The Surgical Treatment of Certain Psychoses, n.a, undated (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Sustained Attention, the Self, and Psychosurgery, 1955 ca. (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, reports, notes on Thorotrast [1/3], 1935-1936 (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, reports, notes on Thorotrast [2/3], 1935-1936 (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, reports, notes on Thorotrast [3/3], 1935-1936 (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Thorotrast in Neurologic Diagnosis, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Transorbital Lobotomy in the State Mental Hospital, Cherokee, Iowa by Willard C. Brinegar, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Freeman treated 32 of these cases
    - Tuberculous Hepatitis with Hypoglycemia in a Diabetic, 1931 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Tumor of the Spinal Cord Localized by Lipiodal, 1928 ca. (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Undercutting Lobotomy in the Aged by W.B. Scoville and V. Gerald Ryan, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Velasco-Suarez and the Early Days of Psychosurgery [follow-up of 17 lobotomy cases, 1942-1943] (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Books, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.7
    - "Psychosurgery: Intelligence, Emotion and Social Behavior, Following Prefrontal Lobotomy for Mental Disorders" by Walter Freeman and James Watts (with Thelma Hunt) Manuscript of first edition, 01/1942 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Brochure for Freeman's book The Psychiatrist, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Reviews of Psychosurgery, 1942-1952 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Unused drawings for 2nd edition of Psychosurgery, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Janet, Pierre. Translated by Walter Freeman. Psychologic Medicine. Paris, France, 1923 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Freeman, Walter. Neuropathology: The Anatomical Foundation of Nervous Diseases. Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders Company, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings and Articles, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.8
    - News clippings and magazine articles: General, 1930-1980 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.9
    - Photographs: Brain, rostral and caudal surfaces, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Photographs: Brain, with labels of various sections (from Richard Lindenberg), 1960 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Photographs: Egas Moniz gives Walter Freeman an award, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      with negative
    - Photographs: Freeman and James Watts posing with portraits hung in Himmelfarb Library, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Photographs: Freeman and son Franklin walking on boardwalk, 1960 ca. (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Photographs: Freeman at Charles Thomas Publisher exhibit, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Photographs: Freeman in suit and tie, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      3 color slides
    - Photographs: Freeman on the Appalachian Trail, 1951 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Photographs: Freeman operating (possibly on Francis Farmer); Freeman and his wife Marjorie; Freeman and Egas Moniz, 1940 ca. (Box 21, Folder 10)
      photocopy
    - Photographs: Freeman operating on patient on gurney, 1950 ca. (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Photographs: Freeman with a backpack in mountains, 1960 ca. (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Photographs: Freeman with group of people, 1950 ca. (Box 21, Folder 13)
      2 copies
    - Photographs: Freeman with son Franklin sitting on a bed, 1965 ca. (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Photographs: Freeman with sons Paul and Franklin at Stanford University, 06/1952 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Photographs: Freeman with three men at Marlboro State Hospital, in front of exhibit on psychosurgery, 11/1953 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Photographs: Freeman, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Photographs: Mario Fiamberti (introduced transorbital lobotomy in 1937), inscribed to Walter Freeman, 1946 ca. (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Photographs: Moniz, Egas and wife, 08/20/1947 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Photographs: Oil portrait of Freeman by Robert Fantuzzi, 1970 ca. (Box 21, Folder 20)
      in color, with slide
    - Photographs: Oil portrait of Freeman by Robert Fantuzzi, 1970 ca. (Box 21, Folder 21)
      black and white, 3 copies
    - Photographs: Oil portrait of Freeman, 1947 ca. (Box 21, Folder 22)
      2 copies black and white, 1 color, 1 slide
    - Photographs: Oil portrait of Freeman, 1947 ca. (Box 21, Folder 23)
      black and white, 2 copies and slide
    - Photographs: Walter Freeman with R. Donahue, 1955 ca. (Box 21, Folder 24)
    - Photographs: Walter Freeman, 1916 (Box 21, Folder 25)
    - Photographs: Walter, Lorne, Franklin Freeman on top of Old Rag Mountain, 11/1948 (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - Photographs: Williams, Freeman, Haas, Hohlen at Yankton State Hospital, 1948 (Box 21, Folder 27)
    - Photographs: 3x4 Photographs of Oil Paintings, undated (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - Artifacts, 1918-1972; MS0803 Suberies 1.10
    - Artifacts: Leather case, with green lettering "Dr. Walter Freeman" contains 2 heavy duty TOL leucotomes (used when roof of the orbit was so tough it was not possible to swing leucotome in an arc and cut the pathways in the frontal lobes of the brain), undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Artifacts: Leather case, with gold lettering "Dr. Walter Freeman" contains 2 TOL leucotomes (used for cutting white matter of the brain, was inserted beneath upper eyelid, through the skull to depth of 7cm and swung on a 20 degree medial arc and 30 degree lateral arc), undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Artifacts: 2 curved leucotomes, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Artifacts: Ice pick labeled: Yolland Ice & Fuel Company Phone 5100 (May have been used by Freeman to perform transorbial lobotomies), undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Artifacts: Three large audio discs, about 20 1/2 inches across, 03/06/1940 (Box 50, Folder 1)
      (Presto Recording Corp. New York) Handwritten note reads: These recordings were made by Dr. Edmund Ziman of St. Eliz. Hosp. in the spring of 1941 to go along with the film on prefrontal lobotomy that was shown at the Am. Psych. Assn meeting in Richmond. The technical problems were too great, however, and the sound was later dubbed in on the operative technic part of the film. The patient was Wm. Mothershead and the first recording was made the day before his operation
  - Walter Freeman restricted materials, Series 1 Subseries 11
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries contains restricted materials that have been removed from the other subseries in this series. The materials in this series reveal the identies of Dr. Freeman's psychiatric patients through the use of names or facially-recognizable photographs.
    Conditions Governing Access
    This subseries is entirely closed to research. Requests for access should be addressed to Special Collection staff.
- James Watts Papers, 1926-1982; MS0803 Series 2; 12.5 Linear feet (Box 42, Box 33, Box 34, Box 31, Box 32, Box 29, Box 30, Box 27, Box 28, Box 35, Box 43, Box 40, Box 41, Box 38, Box 39, Box 36, Box 37, Box 24, Box 23, Box 26, Box 25)
  This series comprises the papers of Dr. James W. Watts and ranges in date from 1926-82. It has the following divisions correspondence; personal papers; manuscripts; publications; conferences papers, lectures; research; photographs; videos and film, and artifacts.
  The correspondence includes letters from Gerald Ford, Egas Moniz, and family members. They are arranged alphabetical and range in date from 1931-82.